A Guide to the Elwood Street, Virginia Courthouse Histories, 1941-1971
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Elwood Street, Virginia Courthouse Histories, 1941-1971
Falls Church History Room, Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Record Group 5-6
2 boxes
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The files were donated by Elwood Street.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
...
Biographical/Historical Note
This project was begun by Elwood Street in 1941. Street visited Virginia county courthouses and wrote articles that were published weekly in the Richmond Times-Dispatch from 1941 to 1942. He retired to Falls Church in 1961 and presented a scrapbook of these articles to the then director of the Falls Church Public Library, Richard Burns. Mr. Burns proposed to the Board of Directors of the Virginia Library Association that the materials of 1941-42 be supplemented by updated information and to publish them in one or more volumes called "Wellsprings of Democracy." The proceeds were to be donated to the Virginia Library Association.This project was begun by Elwood Street in 1941. Street visited Virginia county courthouses and wrote articles that were published weekly in the Richmond Times-Dispatch from 1941 to 1942. He retired to Falls Church in 1961 and presented a scrapbook of these articles to the then director of the Falls Church Public Library, Richard Burns. Mr. Burns proposed to the Board of Directors of the Virginia Library Association that the materials of 1941-42 be supplemented by updated information and to publish them in one or more volumes called "Wellsprings of Democracy." The proceeds were to be donated to the Virginia Library Association.
In 1971 letters were written to the libraries of the Virginia cities and counties asking for updated information and photographs. A Fact Sheet and notes on writing the courthouse histories were included with the solicitations. Many counties responded and the results are in these files. It does not appear, however, that these volumes were ever published.
The Falls Church History Room does hold the scrapbooks of Mr. Street which contain the original newspaper articles published by the Richmond Times-Dispatch: "Wellsprings of democracy: the stories of fifty-five Virginia County Courthouses published by the Richmond Times Dispatch, August 1941-September 1942" by Elwood Street.
Scope and Content
In addition to the courthouse histories, the files include drafts, correspondence, photographs and negatives. The amount of information varies by county.
Arrangement
The files are in order by county name. Each has a history of the courthouse and most have additional information. A list of the courthouse histories with the author(s)' names and dates are listed under the file folder name.
Contents List
- Introduction to "Wellsprings of Democracy," miscellaneous papers and correspondence, "Wellsprings of Democracy: A Lively History of Various Virginia County Courthouses: introduction" (Box-folder 1-1)
- County Courthouses in Review, "County Courthouses in Review" by Elwood Street, 1942 (15 pages) "Why, and How, and Who" by Elwood Street and Richard K. Burns [n.d.] (2 pages) (Box-folder 1-2)
- Accomack County, 1942, "Accomack County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 1942 (17 pages) (Box-folder 1-3)
- Alexandria, 1966, "Alexandria Courthouses" by Ellen Coolidge Burke, 1966 (4 pages) (Box-folder 1-4)
- Arlington County, 1969, "Arlington County Court House" by Jeanne Rose, 1969 (8 pages) (Box-folder 1-5)
- Bedford County, 1937, "Courthouses of Bedford County, Virginia" by Lula Jeter Parker, 1937 (32 pages) (Box-folder 1-6)
- Brunswick County, 1966, "The Brunswick County Court House" by Faith B. Henning, 1966 (8 pages) (Box-folder 1-7)
- Campbell County, 1966, "Campbell County Courthouse, 1781-1966" by Mrs. Marian Asher Fawcett [1966] (16 pages) (Box-folder 1-8)
- Charles City County, 194_, "Charles City County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194_ (15 pages) (Box-folder 1-9)
- Charlotte County, [n.d.], "Charlotte Courthouse: an historical sketch" by Carol B. Charlton [n.d.] (20 pages) (Box-folder 1-10)
- Culpeper County, 1966, "Culpeper Courthouse" by Crimora Waite [1966] (20 pages) (Box-folder 1-11)
- Elizabeth City County and Hampton City, 1966, "From Canoe to Capsule: Brief History of the Courthouse at Hampton" by Mrs. Hamilton H. Evans, 1966 (18 pages) "Elizabeth City County Courthouse at Hampton" by Mrs. Hamilton H. Evans, 1966 (8 pages) "Elizabeth City County and its 'Firsts'" [n.d.] (18 pages) (Box-folder 1-12)
- Fairfax County, 1969, "The Courthouses of Fairfax County, Virginia" by Nan Netherton and Ross Netherton, 1969 (13 pages) (Box-folder 1-13)
- Floyd County, 1966, "Floyd Seat was Named for Jackson" by Raymond Barnes, World-News, June 18, 1966 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Franklin County, 1966, "History of the Franklin County Courthouse" by Josephine Shearer Robinson, 1966 (30 pages) (Box-folder 1-15)
- Giles County, 1966, "History of Giles County Courthouse" by Mrs. C.A. McClaugherty, 1966 (26 pages) (Box-folder 1-16)
- Gloucester County, 1941, 1971, "Gloucester County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 1941 (8 pages) "Changes of 30 Years" by Mrs. William DeHardit, February 1971 (1 page) (Box-folder 1-17)
- Greensville County, 1966, "History and Account of Greensville County Courthouse" by Doris Duncan [n.d.] (16 pages) (Box-folder 1-18)
- Halifax County, 1966, "Wellsprings of Democracy: The History of Virginia Courthouses: The Halifax County, Va., Court-House, Halifax, Va." By Nathaniel H. Wooding, M.D. [n.d.] (4 pages) (Box-folder 1-19)
- Henrico County, 1942, 1971, "Henrico County Sets Example" by Elwood Street, 1942 (30 pages) "Change comes to Henrico Courthouse" by James D. Clark, Jr., 1971 (2 pages) "Courthouses of Henrico and Chesterfield" by William H. Gaines, Jr., Winter 1968 (5 pages) (Box-folder 1-20)
- Isle of Wight County, 1971, "Isle of Wight County Courthouses" by Segar Cofer Dashiell, February, 1971 (12 pages) "Isle of Wight County Stands for Ham," 1971 (21 pages) (Box-folder 1-21)
- James City County, 194_, "James City County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194-, (17 pages) (Box-folder 1-22)
- King George County, 1925-194_; 1971, "King George County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194_ (13 pages) "King George County" as written by Thomas Lomax Hunter in 1936 (6 pages) (Box-folder 1-23)
- Lancaster County, 1940-1971, "Lancaster County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194_ (19 pages) "Courthouses of Lancaster County, 1656-1950," Abstracted and Compiled from the County Court Records by Elizabeth Combs Peirce [n.d.] (pamphlet, 8 pages) "Changes of Thirty Years" by Eleanor G. Keppel, 1971 (1 page) "Old Lancaster County Looks to Future" [n.d.] (19 pages) (Box-folder 1-24)
- Lynchburg City, 1966, "Lynchburg Court House" by Ruth H. Blunt, May 1966 (51 pages) (Box-folder 1-25)
- Mathews County, 194_, 1971, "Courthouse of Mathews County" by Elwood Street, 194_ (10 pages) "Thirty Years Later" by William B. Smith, 1971 (1 page) (Box-folder 2-26)
- Mecklenburg County, [n.d.], "History of Mecklenburg County Courthouse" by Sterling Hutcheson [n.d.] (16 pages) "Mecklenburg County Jails," by Herbert F. Hutcheson, Jr. [n.d.] (4 pages) (Box-folder 2-27)
- Middlesex County, 194_, 1971, "Middlesex County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194_ (9 pages) "More Material from 1971 County Clerk" (1 page) (Box-folder 2-28)
- New Kent County, 1941, 1971, "New Kent County Courthouse," original article by Elwood Street, 1941, (5 pages); revised by Hunter W. Martin, February, 1971 (7 pages) "The Little Courthouse in New Kent County," [n.d.] (6 pages) (Box-folder 2-29)
- Norfolk, 194_-1971, "History of Norfolk Courthouses," by Virginia H. Pinkerton [1966] (11 pages) "Norfolk County Courthouse," by Elwood Street, 194_, (20 pages) "Recent Norfolk Court Developments, by Charles B. Cross, Jr., February 1971 (1 page) "The Norfolk Courthouses," by Virginia H. Pinkerton, 1966 (5 pages) (Box-folder 2-30)
- Northampton County, 1942, "Northampton County Courthouse," by Elwood Street, 1942 (21 pages) "Thirty Years Later, 1971 (1 page) (Box-folder 2-31)
- Northumberland County, 194_-1971, "Old Northumberland," by Elwood Street, 194_ (18 pages) "Thirty Years Later" by Emeline A. Hall, 1971 (1 page) (Box-folder 2-32)
- Nottoway County, 1966, "A Brief History of Nottoway Courthouse, Virginia," by A. R. Cummins, 1966 (15 pages) (Box-folder 2-33)
- Patrick County, 1968, "Patrick County Court House" by Albert F. Allison, 1968 (20 pages) (Box-folder 2-34)
- Prince George County, [n.d.], "War is an Old Story to Prince George" [n.d.] (21 pages) (Box-folder 2-35)
- Princess Anne County, 1966, "Princess Anne Court House," by Margaret C. Capps, Compiler, 1966 (29 pages) "Princess Anne County Courthouse" by Margaret C. Capps, Compiler, 1966 (6 pages) (Box-folder 2-36)
- Prince William County, 1966, "Prince William County Courthouse," by Gladys Bushong, 1966 (13 pages) (Box-folder 2-37)
- Pulaski County. [n.d.], "From the Unpublished 'History of Pulaski County,'" by Daniel A. Cannaday [n.d.] (9 pages) (Box-folder 2-38)
- Roanoke City, 1966, "History of Roanoke Municipal Buildings" by Raymond P. Barnes [1966] (24 pages) (Box-folder 2-39)
- Roanoke County [n.d.], "History of Roanoke County Court House" by Raymond P. Barnes [n.d.] (18 pages) (Box-folder 2-40)
- Rockingham County, [n.d.], "Rockingham County's Stately Court House Fifth Erected on Public Square" by J. Reherd Lineweaver, [n.d.] (17 pages) "Rockingham County Jails" [n.d.] (2 pages) "U. C. Court House" [n.d.] (1 page) "County Court Houses" by Dr. John W. Wayland [n.d.] (9 pages) (Box-folder 2-41)
- Russell County, 1966, "The History of the Russell County Courthouses," by Mrs. Turner A. Gilmer [Vera Duff Gilmer], May 1966, (25 pages) (Box-folder 2-42)
- Stafford County, 1941, "Virginia's County Courthouse Represents the Wellspring of Democracy," [n.d.] (8 pages) "Stafford County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 1941 (6 pages) (Box-folder 2-43)
- Surry County, 194_, "Surry County Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194_, (18 pages) (Box-folder 2-44)
- Tazewell County, 1966-1967, "History of Tazewell County Courthouse," [1967] (9 pages) (Box-folder 2-45)
- Warwick County, 194_, "Old Warwick is Little Changed by Time," [n.d.] (16 pages) "Warwick County" by Elwood Street, 194_ (16 pages) (draft) (Box-folder 2-46)
- Westmoreland County, 1941, 1971, "Westmoreland County Court House" by Elwood Street as of 1941 (17 pages) "Westmoreland County Court House" by Elwood Street with additions made by H. Harfod McKenny [n.d.] (17 pages) (Box-folder 2-47)
- York County, 194_, "York Courthouse" by Elwood Street, 194_ (16 pages) (Box-folder 2-48)